There was an interesting report from MIT
a couple weeks ago that basically said
95% of agentic projects fail. But the
reason for that failure is likely 99% of
engineers, programmers, developers,
project managers don't know how to
actually build aic system.
>> The foundation that you created, the
agentics foundation, what's the problem
it's trying to solve?
>> Let me be honest. AI gives you sort of
delusions of brand. But there was a
group of us and we saw a spectrum. We
saw on one end we had these vibe coders
and what we were doing is creating
architectures and process and approaches
that were repeatable with a defined
outcome and what we saw was the the term
agentics and agentic engineering was
starting to be co-opted by large
companies who are essentially saying it
was an agent but it was a chatbot or it
was a vibe coding system. So we're the
stonemasons or this new emerging field
of gentic engineering for AI.
>> One of the things that came out of the
foundation was spark. What was the
driving force? We saw that a lot of the
early work within these coding systems
were limited by the specification
itself. But once we started looking at
how do we create larger more complex
application it be it became important to
create a specification that the AI could
implement test and verify.
[Music]
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
Now, we've had amazing guests like
Olivier Pomel, the CEO of Data Dog,
Matty Stanisowski, the co-founder of 11
Labs, Victor Ripelli, the CEO and
co-founder at Synthesia, and of course,
Tessle's very own Patrick Dwis. and
they're all sharing lessons right from
the frontier of our industry. A really
quick ask, 90% of people who are
listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So, if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. It
really does help us keep bringing the
folks who are actually pushing this
space forward and helping build that AI
native future. All right, back to the
episode. Hello and welcome to another
episode of the AI Native Dev. My name is
Simon Maple and I'm going to be the host
for today's episode. Uh and joining me
today is Ruven Cohen. Uh people may you
may know him better as REV and and Ruv
is an Agentic engineer. He's the founder
of the Agentics Foundation and also
creator of uh Claude Flow, which you may
have heard about getting a lot of noise
and a lot of adoption just recently. So
Reuben, welcome to the show. How are
you?
>> I'm great. Thanks for having me today.
>> Absolutely pleasure. Whereabouts are you
uh calling in from today?
>> I'm just outside of Toronto, Canada.
Nice sunny late summer day here. So
>> wonderful. Wonderful. Sounds good.
Sounds good. Now um Agentic, when we
think about roof, we always think it's a
gentic foundation, aentic development
with all the things that you've done in
and around Spark and in around Claude
Flow. Um you've been working with
Agentic processes for for years now.
Tell us what it is. Let's let's start
really talking about the state of
Agentic before we kind of like move into
guardrail spark and claude flow. We'd
love to talk about the basics. What is
agentic coding? What what what's the
difference between the core difference
between agentic coding and non-aggentic?
What what makes the difference?
>> Well, it's been a bit of an evolution
for us in in the space. And to tell you
about Agentics, I have to tell you sort
of the brief history of Agentics. And
for some people, it's a long history.
You know, the idea of agents in
technology have has been around for
almost as long as there's been servers
and computers where you'd have systems
that essentially ran sort of, you know,
at a autonomously. So, the idea of an
agent really speaks to the idea of
agency. It the ability to operate with
little to no human oversight. Now a lot
of the early you know agents you would
see in applications things like networks
and other other com components you know
were were very procedural. They would
run specifically within a very confined
structure a you know 1 + 1 equals two.
But as soon as you went outside of that
sort of deterministic sort of
perspective it they fell down. They
weren't smart. They weren't capable.
They just did specifically what they
were programmed to do and nothing else.
And what we saw really with the
emergence of of the GPT models really
GPT3 and beyond was the ability to use a
kind of language alongside of these
systems that were then able to use the
tools and the infrastructure and the
environment in new and interesting ways.
And the major breakthrough we had
probably around two years ago was this
idea of a kind of recursive loop. Now, a
lot of the early agents and and and
prompt engineering were were focused on
a kind of chain of of thought, right? Do
do these things and execute and based on
a kind of language abstraction. But it
turned out what really made these
systems work well was this kind of
recursion feeding errors and logs and
and successes and failures back into the
system so the system could understand
the context of what was happening. Once
we sort of determined that the context
of of what was happening was more
important almost in what was happening,
we could then solve the problems. If
there's an error in code, which almost
always happens, you would be able to
resolve those errors because you the the
AI or the the agents themselves could
understand what those errors are and
resolve them through a kind of uh
feedback loop of sorts.
So here we are 2025 the that this space
u an agentic engineer didn't even exist
probably three years ago. And one of the
as we sort of start building a lot of
this technology is what we ended up
seeing other like-minded sort of
individuals kind of coalescing around
myself and others. You know we had
Reddit groups and WhatsApp and discords
and and then we saw large companies
adopting the the same uh terminology
agentics and agentic engineering. So
it's been a kind of wild ride over the
last really few years here. the idea of
this iterative kind of like process
whereby we can we'll try something if it
doesn't work we'll feed it back in and
kind of like just you know looping this
this this nature of trying again
multiple times before it provides you
with an answer what what do you feel has
made potentially 2025 the was 2025 the
year of the agent or 2024 I can't
remember but but you know when we talk
about the year of the agent is it the
ability for humans to be able to trust
AI to do these things uh um by itself
much much more because when we think
about how developers would use uh AI and
LLM in their coding it kind of very very
much started off with very very much
kind of like autocomplete style uh
suggestions from an assistant and then
we gradually allowed it to do more
whether it was cursor or or other tools
that that kind of like did much more for
us across multiple files and things like
that. What what was the thing do you
feel that really kind of like allowed us
to turn agents on in our code
generation? Is it is it context? Is it
trust from from humans in the process?
Is it the capabilities of LLMs? I don't
think it's trust. I think anyone that's
building these systems inherently
doesn't trust the output and needs to
spend quite a bit of time verifying that
what it's actually given us is true and
valid and functional and not just a kind
of mock or simulated version of what we
asked it. So there's a tendency for the
system to to you know kind of take the
shortest path to give you the the the
outcome. So a lot of what an engineer is
doing is is is working with solid
structures, architectures and other
things to to sort of validate what's
being built is is just functionally true
and correct. Now to your question of
what makes 2025 the year of of sort of
agentics if if that's if that's even a
thing is
one of the big breakthroughs last year
was again this idea of recursion. So um
we a group of us we created these were
kind of systems that could operate on a
kind of long horizon. These are agents
that could run for for hours or days at
a at a time and and then eventually
complete whatever problem they they were
given. Now, the drawback to that, we
could run it for third, I think I did a
36-hour test mostly just to show that I
could run an agent, you know, for 36
hours, but the costs were prohibitively
expensive. And what we saw as we scaled
these agents is a lot of the to to
effectively run this, you're looking at
even on a minimal basis around $4,000
a day. And when we really cranked it up
to, you know, dozens of agents running
concurrently, we're looking at $7,500 US
an hour to run uh at at this at a a 10
agent swarm concurrently basically. And
the it's just it's substantially cheaper
to hire a person at that per at that
point to do that work. It's just even
though you could you could do a ton of
output, most applications didn't require
that level of of scale or capacity. So
in April of this year, what we saw was
uh Anthropic and Claude Code came out
and they started offering a sort of
unlimited all you could eat buffet for
for for tokens and capability. And the
first thing we did is we re sort of
imagined the previous iterations of the
what we called the Spark protocol which
allowed for that recursion. And suddenly
we were able to to spawn these swarms
that could run for hours on end and cost
a flat fee. Often 20 starting at $20,
you know, for an entire month, which is
went from thousands of dollars to $20,
you know, thousands of dollars an hour
to $20 a month. So we saw this
interesting inflection of both
capability. So suddenly we we were able
to build things dramatically faster and
more with a lot more capability at an
exponentially lower cost which is an
interesting sort of you don't generally
see that happen all at once and that was
basically May.
>> Yeah. And that's super interesting
because I think it's that both the
making it more affordable but also the
parallelization it really opens up uh
the the quality of what we can actually
get back as well as as a response. I
want to talk about that in just a
second. Before we move on to to Swarms
and and and Spark specifically, um I'd
love to talk a little bit about the
foundation that you created, the
Agentics Foundation. Um first of all,
the Agentics Foundation isn't kind of
like super new, I guess. Tell us a
little bit about what um you know, what
the need was for that foundation. What's
what's the problem it's trying to solve?
>> It's an it's an organic sort of
evolution of of the work. And I'm going
to tell you a little backstory, which is
going to probably make me sound
absolutely crazy, but I'm going to say
it anyway. So, I was early in into Chat
GBT. I was lucky enough to be an early
beta tester. Uh, I think they called it
a VIP program back in in 2022 with Open
AI. And, you know, so I basically means
I got it maybe three or four weeks
before everybody else. And one of the
first things I asked it is is how can I
be and this is going to sound really
egotistical, but how can I be the most
influential person in AI is what I asked
ChatGBTV1 pre-launch. And it and it gave
me this this sort of step-by-step
process that said, you know, first of
all, what are you good at? What do you
like? And what you know, what where
where do you want to be in a few years?
And it it suggested that anything worth
doing takes years of sort of prep and
and you know, to get to that point. and
and it g it set it gave me this outline
based on a kind of Q&A that you'd have
with chat GBT and most of you have ever
used chat GBT and know know the kind of
you know asking open-ended question sort
of routine and it said basically you're
going to have to build a social media
following and you should be narrow in
that focus and and some I'm asking well
what does that actually mean it says
well what do you like to do and I like
to build autonomous things I I've been
building cloud infrastructure for nearly
25 years that sort of thing and it set
me down this path path and said, "First
of all, you need to create a a
subreddit." Now, I know nothing of
Reddit or subreddits, but I did it. I
followed the guidance and and you know,
three and a half years later, I've got
100,000 plus subscribers of the
subreddit. I'm not really sure exactly
why or what I'm going to do with this
subreddit. It's it but it's popular. And
then it said I needed to do and and the
key was consistency. It said it it told
me that I needed to build a following by
constantly posting interesting things
that I'm doing and sharing those things
publicly on my GitHub, creating weekly
um you know live casts where I can
interact with people. I followed the
guidance and next thing you know I I I
have, you know, thousands and thousands
of people, you know, showing up for
these these live casts, following me and
and essentially buying my time on a kind
of only only fans for geeks sort of
approach where people can sort of
essentially buy my my time on an hourly
basis. And and and the craziest part of
the whole story is it it actually
worked. And I now I I'm I'm I'm in a
fortunate position where I I can claim,
you know, more than a 100 customers, 20
Fortune Fortune 500 clients. I'm
literally one guy, one company. Um you
know, company one and my my wife
actually helps with with some of the
non-technical parts, but generally
speaking, it's me and my bots. And the
entire sort of business plan and process
was literally set forth by ChatGpt V1,
which is in itself just amazing to me.
Did the LLM tell you to create the
foundation or was that something that
you've
>> The foundation was an evolution of those
early conversations? No, it did. It
didn't exactly say that. And what
happened was as the as the community
coalesed around the concepts of Agentics
and the sort of practical approaches
that we were taking to implement the
Agentic systems, it became pretty clear
that we were in the midst of a new
profession. And and when you look
historically at different professions
and and and maybe and and let me let me
be honest, AI gives you sort of you know
delusions of grandeur often but the in
this particular case there was a group
of us and we we're realizing that we are
all practicing a sort of similar
approach to the sort of engineering of
AI and and and when you when we looked
at it we saw a spectrum. We saw on one
end we had these vibe coders. These vibe
coders are not I'm not saying that vibe
coding isn't important. It's a great
ideation, learning and discovery sort of
mechanism, but it's very free form. It's
very it's very fluid in in what you're
doing without really much of a plan. And
what we were doing was different. What
we were doing is creating architectures
and process and and approaches that were
repeatable with a defined outcome that
that was an engineering activity. And
what we saw was the the the term
agentics and agentic engineering was
starting to be co-opted by large
companies who were essentially kind of
AI washing the concept. There were they
were saying it was an agent but it was a
chatbot or it was a vibe coding system.
And we saw this as an opportunity for us
to say well this is our approach. This
is what we believe an agentic engineer
as a professional as a profession should
encompass both technically as well as
the sort of ideas of almost like a like
a guild but for our group of of
engineering right so we're the
stonemasons for this new emerging uh
field of of you know aentic engineering
for AI that and the group formed around
that it's open it's it's the sort of
antithesis of some of the corporate um
open groups open AI sort of being the
other end of the spectrum you know
dominated by corporate interests we said
we need to make this for people to sort
of empower them both professionally and
maybe there's some more aspirational but
as a as the society around AI takes
shape what does that actually look like
and how do we protect the interests of
the people ultimately that are going to
be affected by it most so we act we want
anyway to act as a kind of hedge against
trillion dollar companies um if we can
do that and that was formed in March of
this year and next thing you know we're
in something like 60 cities. We've got
event multiple events sort of organic
startups or you know meetups all around
the uh all around the world happening
every week
>> and people can just join that. How do
people what's the best way to people for
people to kind of like get involved?
>> Well, we've got a a lot of the communic
the the communication and community
happens around either our Discord
channel discord.agentics.org
or WhatsApp. Our WhatsApp's maxed out,
so I'm not going to give you the address
because, you know, when you hit the
certain threshold, you basically can't
add anybody. Um, but uh most of it we've
shifted to Discord at this point. And
Gentix.org, it's a again a member-ledd
organization, meritocracy if you will.
So the if you if you want to get
involved, you want to create a new
chapter in a different city, do a
meetup, basically you just volunteer and
we make it happen. So if we were to look
at the states of Agentic today, what
would you say are kind of the things
that are creating that ceiling for for
for Agentic today? What are what are the
biggest things that causing Agentic uh
development to to fail or at least to to
to cause problems to developers trying
to use Agentic development today?
>> The limiting factors of the space right
now. And there was an interesting report
from MIT a couple weeks ago, I think it
was, that basically said 95% of agentic
projects fail. And it was a a fair a
fairly sort of sensational title. And
and when you when you dig into that a
little bit, you there there's two ways
to to to think about those types of sort
of stats. one,
you know, 95% of projects fail, which is
probably true, but the reason between
for that failure is likely 99% of of
engineers, programmers, developers,
project managers don't know how to
actually build aic systems and it's a
byproduct of a new emerging space. And
it and it's so the the limiting factor
is the fact that it's really hard to to
look beyond the sort of um you know I
call it AI washing the agentic washing
of products and the and the people
associated with it to determine you know
what the capabilities of the products
and the people implementing these
products really are. So when you see
this sort of high failure rate it speaks
to the fact that we're in a new emerging
space. And when you go, if you're old
enough to have been around at the
beginning of the internet, you would
have seen the same thing with a lot of
the internet projects that corporations
took on back in the late 90s and there
was this sort of, you know, this idea
that the internet wasn't quite going to
cut it for most business type
applications. And then they were wrong.
It was the fact that we didn't as a
industry understand exactly how to build
userfriendly internet-based
applications. And over time there were
models to follow. Amazon's and the eBays
and whatnot showed up and we're like
okay this is how you create a web-based
service that people can easily interact
with and it's not just recreating
software. same problem 25 years later,
30 years later in the agentics and AI
space. There's a tendency for people to
build applications the way they've
always built them with with human
centric models, uh, review cycles, long
drawn out sprints, um, and different
sort of, you know, traditional tactics
that were optimized for a world where we
built slowly over time and gradually.
Now, we're in a world where we can
literally copy anything anywhere at at a
moment's notice. and the ability the the
quality of the code although important
is less important than the momentum that
you get in terms of speed and time to
market. So when you're looking at
companies that are embracing this
they're they're embracing this in a way
that doesn't just replace their
developers that that might be a
byproduct but it augments them in ways
that those developers were never able to
do before. So you're empowering them
with sort of a kind of superpower to to
to create much more effectively and much
more quickly which in itself creates a
whole variety of secondary problems. But
ultimately this is this is the
empowerment of developers to to do more
with less. And a lot of the the kind of
like ways in which that can be done um
in a in a more predictable way I guess
is to use rails or guard rails. Um one
of the things that that came out of the
foundation I believe uh was spark s
um
talk us through a little bit about what
kind of was the driving force behind
spark. uh was it was it pain in terms of
you know seeing how people or yourselves
were being able to develop code and what
the different kind of angle or
perspectives you needed from that
because I know it's obviously very
specificationbased but there are also a
number of different things beyond just
specifications which are important to to
allow your aentive processes to build in
a predictable way.
>> Exactly. And what we saw if you if you
rewind about a year and a half, we saw
that a lot of the early work within
these uh coding systems even before
agents became sort of popular were
limited by the specification itself. And
a lot of the development was happening
on a kind of function by function basis.
Fix this, copy and paste this into the
system and and as you said it kind of
autocomplete, which was fine and and
that was not a bad starting point. But
once we start looking at how do we
create larger more complex applications
with interconnected relationships, data
structures, user experience components,
infrastructure, it be it became
important to create a specification that
the AI could follow, implement, test and
verify. Now part of that it was an
homage to some of the work I did 25
years ago with Sun Micros Systemystems
and their Spark processor. I'm not going
to lie, this the Spark with a C. and and
uh AI is pretty good at creating
acronyms and as anyone can see the RUV
stands for something new every other day
for me but ultimately the the
specification allowed for a kind of
specification that said here's what I'm
building a PRD if you will and then
rather than building the entire
specification what what I ended up doing
was saying I need to create a pseudo
code outline though so I'm not trying to
build the entire code obviously that's
going to happen at a later stage what I
want to do is create a scaffolding
allows the AI to understand the general
structure of what the code needs to look
like before it implements it. So the
second stage was basically a kind of
rudimentary scaffolding of all the parts
of the application. Then we then once we
had that then we have a defined
architecture an architecture that that
would be defined based on the code. Once
we had that then we could go through a
refinement phase that was the iteration.
The refinement provides a mechanism to
say now we have a pseudo code outline
and a defined architecture which
includes all the various parts of the
application. Now we can start actually
start building that the refinement
turned out to be a really interesting
part when we got to the point of
parallel or concurrent development
process. So now that we know exactly all
the parts of the application, we can get
different different agents to work on
different parts of the overall
application independently of each other,
although connected through the
architecture itself using a test-driven
development approach, which is the
completion, the test-driven development
approach. And I'm going to give you a
quick background for those that aren't
familiar with test-driven development.
There are essentially two different
approaches to test-driven development.
the traditional test-driven development
approach, sometimes referred to as the
Detroit school, which is essentially
creating the test as you create the
code. And that's what most test-driven
development today does. You have a
function or or part of an application,
you create a test, you write the code,
it passes, it fails. That was great for
people, but it's not great for
autonomous agents building things. The
other approach was referred to or is
referred to as the London School of
Testriven Development. Now, the London
School of Test Room Development uses a a
scaffolding. It's basically developers
hate it because you're basically
creating the entire application several
times. One, you're creating the entire
much like what I defined in in the Spark
architecture. You're creating the
outline of all the parts and how all the
parts work before you ever build the
application. Then you're building the
application. It fails. It always fails.
Then you're then you're doing it again.
So, you're literally building the
application at least three times,
possibly four times.
But what's interesting about this
approach when you have AI agents is one,
they don't actually complain about
having to do the same work four times.
They they're AI and and you're doing it
really really quickly and concurrently.
So what would take months or many weeks
now can happen in an afternoon and and
that and that provides again a guide for
the AI to follow. And once all those p
all those tests pass generally speaking
assuming there's there not completely
simulated your application works. Now
different languages work better than
others. So there a lot a lot of people
ask what's the optimal language for
this? Well you know there's Python and
there's you know Node and JavaScript and
TypeScript things like that. But the
problem with those languages is they're
permissive. Meaning that these languages
are allow you to build with a lot of
flaws and they they'll they'll basically
work even if they're not right. And then
you have languages like Rust which are
very explicit in in their definition
deterministic. It's really hard to build
bad things in Rust because it just
doesn't work if it's if it's not built
correctly. So by applying a rigid
specification to a a less permissive or
rigid programming language, the
combination gives you the ability to
build really really complicated hard
broad projects and basically know
reliably that it'll work when you're
done.
>> Yeah. And let's dig into a few of those
pieces uh in a bit more depth because
it's really there's so many interesting
things that you kind of like just just
outlined there. First of all with
specifications when when when you when
you look at your specifications and you
talk about the capabilities are you are
you adding effectively highle test cases
as part of the the specification or is
that something that is really done at
the end
>> I'm doing at the beginning so I'm I'm
>> right at the beginning
>> I'm doing at the beginning so uh though
so when you follow the spark and there's
different ways and a lot of people will
massage that to their own needs but
basically what you're doing at you're
creating these sort of requirements the
you know what does the product need to
do how does it need to solve the problem
what are the algorithms what are the
flows the data structures the
authentication you know all the things
you'd want in the application then what
you're doing is saying how do I validate
how do I test that this thing actually
does what it's supposed to do and that
is the biggest challenge you're going to
run into in any of these automated
systems is you know at the end it says
it's done and it's not it's it's a it it
had it's a convincing forgery it's a
it's a fraud and anyone that's ever led
a a sort of uh AI run for a while and
and looked at and says well this isn't
true this isn't right and that that's a
byproduct of an an of a uh specification
that doesn't have the tests adequately
defined to define what is true and what
is not right so when you integrate that
as part of the development flow you can
uh sort of mitigate the potential for
fake or fraudulent sort of results
>> yeah and and it also feels like it's a
far easier thing to describe when you're
talking about the specs and you're
talking about the behavior, you're
effectively describing tests. It's like
it's it's hard to do one without the
other. Um you then mentioned pseudo
code, which is really really
interesting. Um when we talk about when
we at Tesl
we're constantly thinking, okay, should
the specs care about the implementation
at all? How much should it kind of like
deep go deeper into the implementation
or about the how something should be um
created? And there's always a fine
balance between the the the what and the
how. And it sounds like with the pseudo
code, it's interesting that that that
kind of like doesn't necessarily provide
language specific uh information, but it
does provide that ability to be able to
define parts of the infrastructure,
define how I architect this application
to be to be created. Um couple of
questions in there. Um, first of all,
while that I suspect provide gives the
LLM a better way to actually then go
ahead and actually create
implementation, do you find there's a
balance there between how accurate it
can be with the implementation, but also
how um how prescriptive you're being
with the LLM. Does that does that
provide benefits as well as kind of like
drawbacks or do you do you find that
that's like, you know, the the the best
the best of both world solution for it?
I think the prescription prescriptive I
should say is is is a good description
of it. What you're trying to do is is
the more narrow the task the better the
result. So when you look at at you know
a agentbased development a lot of times
people take the analogy of replacing a
developer or persona. It it's not like
that. You're not you're not they don't
operate like people at all. And this
idea that you're trying to replace, you
know, traditional human tasks and and
development approaches with a
agent-based approaches just doesn't
really work. When what you need to look
at this is like a multi-threaded
development process where each thread is
specifically tailored to a particular
narrow problem you're trying to solve
within a much larger group of threads.
And so one thread might be literally a
one function that that that calls a data
or CLI or or some other particular part
and once that's done it it's it's
functional. So an application is made up
of many many many threads that that are
working concurrently to solve that being
tested and as you say it's prescriptive
in how it's defined. Does it actually do
what it's intended to do and did I do a
good enough job of defining what I
wanted originally? Now, sometimes I
don't, right? Sometimes you you're not
really sure what you want to build and
and that's the that's also quite
exciting is to explore the the unknown
and and seeing what I can build uh kind
of in a more vibe style. But that said,
I still need to be prescriptive in the
approach and the tactics that I'm using
to build those things. So what this led
to things like cloud flow which allowed
me to sort of share my development
approach in a way that was open enough
to be interpreted and used in a variety
of different sort of architectures,
methodologies and and applications
themselves, but but narrow enough to do
so in a way that allows people who don't
necessarily know all the things that
they don't know to do it in a way that
wasn't going to result in a bunch of
spaghetti that doesn't work.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And and I guess the
second a second piece to this and I and
I I guess when I when I first started
playing with Kira as a good example, one
of the first things I noticed was when
they when they use specifications, the
spe the the life cycle of the
specification tends to be the change
that they're trying to make. So if I
were to make a change to an existing
application, I would say this is um this
is what I'm trying to do. It would
create a specification based on the
changes it needs to make. it would
create a design style spec as well and
it will create a list of tasks that it
needs to do to actually enact that you
know create that change. um if I were to
then carry on I would probably create a
new specification for a new change it
the life cycle is based on that change
whereas what I'm hearing from you is
more that the life cycle of the
specification is the application or is
it is the specification
is that is that is that I guess kind of
first of all a fair representation of
how you think of specifications and and
also claude flow uh works with
specifications and we'll kind of get on
to cloud flow in just a sec
>> one of the things that I'm doing when
you look at sort of my development is
I'm I'm using so a lot of these systems
are based on the idea of markdown right
you would be able to create a docs
folder plans folder and and in create
specifications those specifications
would probably define multiple phases
where you are in the implementation
strategy and and it would sort of you
know iterate through the those phases
and markdown files. Now the issue that
we faced when looking at that approach
was the fact that it lost context. it
wasn't contextually aware of uh beyond
the last MD file or or if it happens to
look at the other MD files where it was
in the actual development process. So
what I ended up doing was using the
approach of a kind of shared memory
space and and I I I made it simple. A
lot of people were were focused on using
vectors and complex sort of similarity
up you know searches. It turns out you
don't need any of that. Turns out what
you really need is a common uh simple
SQLite storage environment that allows
all the agents to you know save their
current state as well as access the
previous state in in a way that was easy
for any agent participating in the swarm
to see and and interpret. Then that that
that opened up two general directions.
One was a swarm. A swarm uses the
concepts of of sort of independently
operating agents or or sometimes I call
them threads but these agents were
essentially operating with a common
direction kind of orchestrator of sorts
that would tell them generally what to
do and then the each agent would be sort
of autonomous in the sense that they
would be able to make their own
determination how to solve that problem
and then they'd update the status and
and through that sort of shared memory.
The other approach, which uses the
concepts of a hive mind, which sounds
straight up sci-fi, creates a a the
ability for each agent to share the
exact context of what's happening at any
given point rather than rather than
running autonomously, which I would
assume like an ant colony, it might be
an example. Each ant has a task. They
they've got leadership and and are
orchestrated through the pherommones of
the queen, but they are they are
autonomous entities in a sense that they
don't share at least I don't think they
do share conscious constructs between
each each of them. The hive mind allows
you for a common I'm going to call it
consciousness. It's probably the wrong
term a common sort of mind and to
understand what's happening at any given
point and then adjust based on it.
Solves different problems totally
different development tactics. The hive
mind approach is generally better for
broad early development. You know,
you're you're going to build a bunch of
things quickly, you know, hundreds of
thousands of lines of code and you want
it to sort of all more be more
integrated in in the sense swarm is a
little more targeted. So, I think of it
like a sculptor might. You get a big
giant piece of granite, you're blasting
away at it at the beginning. Hide mind.
When I'm getting when I need more
narrow, more details, I need to do the
nose and the ears and the eyes. I'm
going to use swarms and specific parts
of that to really target the different
parts of the thing I want to build. I'm
building the face. I'm not building the
body at this point. The swarm's great
for that. So, you change your tactics
based on where you are in the
development of your application and and
the tools.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And I I guess in terms
of, you know, this this thinking of if
I'm going to make a change or if I'm
going to add something to my
specification, I don't want it to
necessarily regenerate everything.
Is is the hive mind also good at kind of
like recognizing what needs to be
regenerated, what doesn't need to be
regenerated to make sure you almost
preserve that history of of I guess
context of what how everything else has
been built. I guess what does that
workflow look like? It it it's it's
adaptive which is the which is the most
interesting part of these things.
They're they are given a level of
autonomy and a declarative approach to
solve those problems based on the
requirements of the overall project. The
current state of the implementation of
the project does it work? What what's
left to do? And a sort of human in the
loop that guides that process. And
ultimately what what we're doing here is
is a kind of I don't know it's gonna
sound crazy a symbiotic relationship
between the AI itself and me the sort of
developer the swarm master whatever you
want to call it that that helps guide
through the steps. What I'm not
generally doing is letting this thing
run for six hours and you know sometimes
I do but but more I'm doing sprints. I'm
doing hour or two letting it solve the
hard problems. Uh ideulating,
optimizing, you know, and and and then
I'm reviewing then I'm moving on to the
next phase and I'm the I'm the reviewer
and that's an important part of the
process.
>> And as part of that, if if you asked for
something and then it goes away and
actually completely rebuild something,
um so long as the pass the tests pass,
do you care or is that something that
you would consider risk?
>> I I don't trust anything. I val I I I I
validate and verify everything that
happens. Just because it tells me the
test has passed doesn't necessarily mean
I believe it. And and it often now that
I'm I've gotten pretty good at doing
this. When the test pass, it means it is
generally right. But I assume it's
wrong. And I need heavy level of proof
to validate that it's built it in a way
that I like, that it's secure, that it's
scalable, that doesn't hardcoded any env
in the source code. And one of the other
challenges that we have with a lot of
these systems, Claude code in
particular, is the context engineering
itself. It starts off great and after,
you know, 45 minutes of doing whatever
it's doing, it's compacted the
conversation a few times and it's lost
its context. So the reinjection or
reminding a kind of power steering of
sorts for the system is really
important. And and I think tools like
was it R code did did power steering
where you could sort of have a
reminder of where where it is every now
and again it works works really well and
and these systems need to be reminded of
of its purpose and focus.
>> Yeah. And this is something that
actually that that kind of uh Claude
flow does very very nicely as well. I'd
love to kind of jump into Claude Flow
now. Um tell us a little bit about this
is some this is a project tool that you
created. Um uh when did you first
release actually it was it was fairly
recent the last couple of months.
>> June 15th is it was June 15th. Yeah it
was funny and and there's a few things
that that was I learned. I've been on an
epic development um sort of sprint over
the last two months and I' I'm I've lost
count but last I checked I was like
several million lines of code and and a
lot of different roughs projects and
what so the first version was
essentially I discovered something
called the batch tool within cloud code.
The batch tool essentially was an
undocumented part of their system that
allowed me to move from a sequential
implementation of the agent. So, if you
ever use plot code or a lot of these
other systems, you'll notice that it
does task, finishes the task, moves the
next, and moves the next. What the batch
tool allowed me to do was create sub
aents, which interestingly enough,
Anthropic adopted the same term. Thank
you, No credit to me, but whatever. And
then um so with the sub these sub agents
essentially allowed the again the
threads each of these things could run
in a parallel form all at once. So
rather than sequentially, I could spawn
10 or or I think at one point I did 500
of these agents. I generally run in
smaller numbers and odd numbers wherever
possible. And I'm not sure why odd
numbers work better, but they do. And
essentially what that means is there,
you know, one's doing, you know, a a
task, another's doing another task, and
and and then they can all run at the
same time, which took a project that
would take me three or four hours and I
can now do in a half an hour because I
had agents running concurrently rather
than sequentially over over three or
four hours. So the speed was dramatic.
It was basically a linear um increase in
in in sort of capability or that
decrease in in time. So 10 agents is 10
times less than you know and but there's
also a sort of max I noticed that I
really wasn't seeing much improvement
beyond around 20 agents for for things
unless it's maybe doing like machine
learning models and optimization but for
most development centric things it kind
of maxed out around 10 or 15 agents and
I wasn't seeing really any improvement
beyond that and and at which point I
then said okay I I think this is
something that others would want and
because I was doing a lot of work in
Rust. I had concurrently developed a
micro neural network architecture you
where I ported one of the first projects
I did in in the B1 of of the sort of
batch style agents was basically porting
existing complex libraries into Rust.
I'm like what's the most complicated
thing I can possibly build? That's
literally what I was thinking. and and
the first one was the fast uh neural
network project and um which I think is
referred to as fan sometimes. I ported
that into Rust made it a a Wom a web
assembly component that I could run in
the browser on CLIs or or servers
without any requirements. So it's
portable it's light and and was around I
don't know the exact number but
substantially faster than the
traditional C and C++ implementation. I
package that up, put it into cloud uh in
into a sorry mpx so I can deliver that
through a common mpm or mpx uh delivery.
So if you ever install different modules
for for typescript or mo or noode.js,
you do the mpx. So I can deliver these
really complex rustbased components as a
typescript module, meaning I can get it
to anyone anywhere pretty much. And I
created the first version that combined
the idea of a of an adaptive neural
network along with a swarm component and
I called it claude flow launched it and
and suddenly within a matter of hours I
had tens of thousands of downloads of
this thing and and we were sort of
inundating uh anthropic and and I don't
think they were particularly happy about
this. So within a within about a week I
had about 100 thousand downloads and we
were doing you know just billions and
billions of tokens through the system
and I I'm fairly certain we were a large
part of why they revised their um their
model. I'm sorry it wasn't wasn't the
plan you know but they said unlimited.
So in fairness, I I was taking advantage
of of that uh of that of that. And then
that led to a sort of recursive
development where I could improve the
things I was building even faster
because now I had this adaptive neural
network that allowed me to optimize
specific
kind of synaptic components. So micro
neural networks that were interconnected
to each other and self-optimized. So
where traditional neural networks were
monolithic, you'd have billion plus
parameter models, what I was doing was
creating very narrowly focused neural
networks that were explicitly built for
a task. Trade this one stock in a
certain way, understand a particular
customer segment or whatever it needed
to do. And so I was training 10,000 or
maybe 100,000 parameter neural network
models and then applying it to the
actual application to solve the problem.
So we get really really smart at that
one thing. trade that trade a stock
better and and I didn't need a GPU
because I'm using subund,000 parameter
models. No GPU is required. I could
create a neural network in in seconds
based on the Rust library that does the
one thing and no GPU required at all.
which basically changes the paradigms
from a a a monolith to a distributed
sort of synaptic network of many small
interconnected neural networks that all
can collaborate with each other which is
straight up sci-fi.
>> Yeah. No, absolutely. Walk us through if
you can the the or or show us if you can
the the the uh the claw flow in action.
So I'd love to I'd love for the folks
and listeners to almost like see the um
uh I guess the use cases. Would you
would you say it's more for people who
are creating from scratch or would you
say it's more for people who are trying
to convert existing applications into a
spec more specentric uh approach? What
would you say is the is the core use
case that people uh pick up? Claude clo
>> I've been working on a new gamified
version of the system that allows users
to learn how to use it by participating
in challenges and different types of of
sort of gamified version of it. So you
know it it's broad it's it's it's for
everyone from early users to you know a
master aentic engineers and hopefully
everything in between. Um let me give
you a little demo here hopefully. So
this the in a sec I'm what I'm going to
show you here is my um flow nexus
development environment which is a new
project I've been working on. Hopefully
I'll launch it later this week. Let's
see here. What I'm showing you right now
is a code space running in in GitHub.
When you run swarms, remember you're
running in a kind of dangerously skip
permissions mode within cloud, which
means you probably don't want to run
this on a local environment. you can um
if you're using Windows Wows subsystem
WSL and Macs are probably a little more
forgiving. I'm running an Iuntu code
space on uh GitHub in this case. Now to
install, as I mentioned before, I'm
using an MPX or an MPM. Now, you can
install either way. An MPX for those who
aren't familiar allows you to run in a
kind of remote instantiated version. So,
you're always getting the most recent
version. an MPM an MPM style install
which looks something like which looks
something like this installs it globally
but doesn't update it automatically as
you so you don't get the you're getting
kind of a moment in time. So generally
what people are doing is they're running
an MPX and to install it all you're
doing is running claude-flow
at at alpha. This at alpha part
basically means you're getting my my
alpha version and it's it's alpha until
I'm confident that there's no bugs or I
stop developing I suppose. But you're
getting the the you're getting the alpha
version at that point. Now to verify all
you're going to do is is write version.
This is going to this is going to
instantiate. You see I'm running alpha
91. Now once once we have that we can
run the help command. The so this is a
CLI but the CLI is actually and MCP
server I might add is is optimized not
for you to use directly. And this is the
part that sometimes people get confused
by. most of the capabilities of the
system are actually optimized for the
system itself to to use. So for example,
if if I run a command to update the
memory, I could I can invoke that
command directly. Well, in this case,
I'm going oh, I got a Riverside sharing.
So I'm going to I'm going to update the
memory. I'm just going to type this
command session generate summary
persistent. This is but the AI is
intended to do that. So you can see here
I've been running this for 9,700
minutes. I've done 559 edits. So, G. So,
this is basically giving the context.
But if I want to actually build
something, I've got a couple different
ways to build. I've got my my my wizard.
So, I can go you can see here that I've
got different options. So, I've got
training. I've got verification. There's
a ton of stuff in here. Um, so I can
start. I'm just going to run the wizard
this this time. So, I'm just going to
copy this. And this is going to guide
you through the process of running the
wizard. So in this case, I'm just going
to go and and choose alpha and I'm going
to do the hive mind wizard. And this
guides you through different options for
creating swarms, viewing the swarm
status. So the these are the more human
parts of the interface. So I'm going to
create a new swarm. I'm going to to
press the uh you know live cast viewer
viewers uh optional name. I'm just going
to let it do whatever it's whatever it
wants. Now, I've got different
approaches for this for the queen.
Interesting enough, she named herself I
didn't. She named herself Saraphina. Uh,
which is interest I I did a little, you
know, my wife actually when I told her
about this thing, my my swarm gave
herself a name, but she's now our
mascot. So, I'm going to choose I'll
just choose strategic. I'll say seven
agents.
I can choose which agents I want.
And then I can go and I can choose how
the agents come up with their consensus
for making decisions. So I can choose
different types. I generally use
majority. So if I've got a seven agent
swarm, four four agents will will
determine the the the direction when you
generally use odd numbers. Um even
numbers for
>> you. You mentioned that before. Why why
why do you think that is? Uh well even
numbers just you know if two two out of
four or you know five out of 10 you know
just doesn't really work for consensus.
It's funny how when you actually look at
nature you see so many odd numbers or
Fibonacci for example just being used
very very naturally throughout
throughout nature's choices. So it's
it's it's really interesting that that
odd numbers you know it kind of it seems
very poignant to me that that it
naturally chooses odd number or
naturally works better with odd numbers.
>> Yeah. Yeah, it seems to. So, I'm gonna
I'm just gonna do majority autoscaling.
Sure, why not? And then I'm gonna launch
dash. No, I'm not going to bother with
that. Still building that. Um Oh, I had
an error. I'm in my I'm in my dev
environment. So, that that no worries.
We're we're going to invoke that anyway.
So, in this case, I'm going to spawn
uh and then I can give it a title.
Uh create a re
create a five agent swarm
to research
uh I don't know swarms and then I'm
going to add the claw to invoke the
cloud system. In this case I'm going to
go right here. Oh, I'm having I'm having
some trouble with that. I'm going to I'm
going to I'm going to jump the the uh
I'm going to use a swarm instead. That's
the problem with showing you a dev
environment. All right, so we're going
to go here and we're going toh do swarm.
I'm going to use the same uh so there's
two modes,
the hive mine, which apparently is
having an issue at the moment, and the
swarm. So in this case, I'm just going
to do that for this one. Hopefully that
solves that problem.
And there we go. So now we're we're
launching a um an agent. You see that I
injected a bunch of information. This is
basically telling it the MCP tools to
use. and where we've got different sort
of uh options. I I I didn't I'm not
going to do anything. I'm just showing
you sort of the process of spawning the
the swarm itself. Um so now it's it's
initializing the swarm. We'll see that
it'll it'll it'll make use of the CLI
and MCP components on the fly.
And so here we we're oh dev environment.
I I I should have probably prepped a
little bit more, but this this is trying
to invoke the swarm types. Well, we'll
see. It's it's self it's self-fixing. So
we'll we'll uh we'll see what happens.
There we go. It figured itself out. Now
when you when you see these these here,
this indicates that it's an agent. So we
have got colorcoded agents. You can
modify all these things by going into
the agent folder and claude here or the
commands which are the slash commands.
And you'll see that I've got all the
different commands available to it. So
the it it's it's invoking its own sort
of you know persistence. It's it's
creating the tasks. It's using the MCPs
and CLIs to do the sort of coordination
before it then launches the the the
swarm itself.
>> And when you when you talk about the
swarm, would you use the swarm primarily
because you wanted to have different
roles and different perspectives or
would you or do you see it more as a
parallelization task where you're
effectively trying to get 10 things
running at, you know, in the space in
the space of one?
>> Uh, it depends. It depends what you're
trying to do. So in this case, I I gave
it a pretty generic sort of, you know,
guide. It's I said to research swarms,
which isn't really telling it to do
much, you know, more more just to invoke
it more than anything else. So
depending on what you're trying to do,
you you can have different sort of
processes that allow it to to deploy and
work in different manners. So in this
case, if I go here back to the MPX for a
moment, you'll see we'll see different
the different options. So we've got
options here for for training. So this
is doing all the the neural network
components. So you can optimize
monitoring. You can you can do things
those sorts of things. I got a
verification system that handles sort of
defining the you know is it actually
building what it's supposed to is it is
it actually is it truthful? is, you
know, is is it and then I've got the
ability to integrate people into the
process using a kind of collaborative
pair based programming that sort of
integrates the concepts of of, you know,
other participants that aren't AI into
the process. And so lots of different
sort of components depending on what
you're trying to do. So the answer is it
really depends on what problem you're
trying to solve. And that's part of the
idea of an agentic engineering system.
It's meant that you are the active
orchestrator engineer of the process and
and you can make it your own. Right. I I
made this for engineers not necessarily
for vibers directly.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And interestingly when
you mentioned when you talk about vibers
there when we lean more into specs with
things like things like this and you can
kind of like fire off a number of
different agents to kind of like run
things and we get much much longer
running processes. Do you feel like I
I've kind of like, you know, thought
about vibe specking as something now
whereby we're still vibing, but um we're
actually losing contact with our specs a
little bit more in terms of reading them
firsthand. Is that is that something
that you have also kind of like felt a
little bit whereby you're you're more
you're more able to kind of like
interact with an with an LLM on your
specs and then have everything get
generated from there? um or have you
found like the new the new way of
development is about this inter this
direct interaction that we're having
with specifications.
>> The specs are the most important part of
the process and you know people ask me
like how much time am I spending on the
spec versus letting it run. Now, I'm
spending all my time on the spec. The
the letting it run part is just letting
it run, you know, but telling it how to
run is is a particularly important part
of the of the process itself. So,
without a decent PRD or technical
specification, then you're not going to
get a decent output. Are you very
specentric now whereby the source of
truth is the spec? Um, how much do you
then touch code after after actually
generation from the specification? How
much do I touch? Uh I I depends. One of
the one of the things that you'll notice
when you do you know a AIcentric
development is there tends to be a
cognitive offload. It makes you
lazy in some regards and that and I'm
not any different than anybody else you
know. So certain things obviously if I
want to change a title or or do some
text somewhere it's quicker just to up
and edit the thing. But even then
sometimes I have a tendency to just say
Claude go do that which is kind of
silly. I could literally open the file
and edit the the the code in in like 5
seconds. And in that scenario the CL you
know cloud code is going to take you
know longer to do that even but I'm just
lazy right go do that. That's a
challenge right? AI AI for has a
tendency to give you make you powerful
but also make you a little lazy in
certain regards.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Super interesting. What do
you think are the next steps from an
agentic point of view? What where do you
see the agentic future of software
development heading?
>> I think we're we're going to we're going
to get better fidelity. I think we're
we're reaching a we're in the early
stages of this and what I'm showing are
as a kind of leading indicator of what's
possible and what what's capable. Most
there's two schools of thought. When the
people see the stuff that I'm building,
it's what they call AI sloth. It's like
there's no way that this guy could build
so much stuff so quickly and have it be
of any real value or capability. I think
the fact that I I was able to get
hundreds of thousands of users within a
matter of of days of my platforms
indicates that it's probably not. But,
you know, it's hard. It's, you know,
there's so much there. I get and I
understand why people would think that.
There's no way for them to review that.
There's no way for me to effectively
review millions of lines of code. So the
the assumption that it's bad is is
probably um you know understandable but
it but the at the end of the day the
real litmus test for this isn't whether
it's bad or good or whatever is whether
one it's actually solves the problem
it's intended to solve like does it
actually do the thing that you you
wanted it to do. Does it? And then
secondly, maybe primarily does it do it
in a way that's that's effective,
secure, and optimized, right? And and if
you can check off those things, then
that is all that matters. Now, is it
like, you know, artisan code that's
optimized line by line written by, you
know, someone with 50 years of coding
experience? No, it isn't. It's a
different thing. It's it's it's but it
is something that I could create in a
moment to illustrate or I can create
every possibility of a problem and and
choose the best one where where
previously I'd have to choose I have to
make an assumption and go with that
assumption whether it was right or
wrong. I couldn't test every assumption
and choose the best of the assumptions
because it just wasn't enough time in
the day or the cost, you know, was cost
prohibitive. I can do all that now. I
don't even need a team of people. I just
need to ask the right swarm the right
question.
>> Yeah. And what would you say is kind of
like as a as a final question, uh, ROF,
what would you say is your kind of like
the biggest bug bear right now that you
have with with kind of either I guess
agentic flows or LLMs perhaps? um in in
an agentic flow, what would you say is
the biggest problem that if you could
click your fingers and make it disappear
or have a workaround or a solution that
today is causing you the most problems
with your with this kind of you know
nice workflow whether it's through
clawed uh flow or a gentic development
today.
>> Validation I think is still a challenge
and I I think we've discussed this a few
times today. Is it is it true? Is it
real? Is it does it actually do what I
needs to do in the way that I wanted it
to do that thing? And ultimately, that
is the the key here. And that's it's
anyone that's using Cloudflow, pretty
much anyone using any of these systems
that you know are are are suffering
through that a little bit. What
regardless of of Claude or whatever
else, they all they all suffer from that
same problem.
>> Yeah. No, I think it's a very fair
assessment actually and I think it's
something that we'll hear again and
again with validation. And I think it's
super important for trust and actually
just making sure that what this is kind
of you know busy busy building and busy
uh busy developing is uh is is fit for
purpose and and and actually what we
want to we want to deliver. Uh rude this
has been super super useful. I would
love to you you kind of mentioned where
people can you know access to the uh to
the foundation in terms of next steps if
people want to learn more about spark or
if people want to learn more about
claude flow
where do they start? I created a new
landing page finally. I'm like the shoe
maker that doesn't have any shoes for a
while there. But um yeah, I I did end up
creating a landing page. It's done quite
well for me. Um roof ruv.io. You can see
all my various projects and and uh
things that I'm building at any given
time. I'm I'm very prolific on GitHub.
Um githubet
ruvnet.
Um, and uh, you'll see all my various
projects which runs the gamut from
useful to just crazy. You know, that's
I'm just trying to push the boundaries
of what what I can build and what these
systems can do just because
>> valuable to crazy. I you know, you could
call that valuable to inspiring, I
guess. Let's let's let's do that, shall
we?
>> Yeah. I'm I'm not I'm you know, I I know
I'm on the right track when people say
it's not possible and you're crazy like
that. That's like
Perfect. I'm looking I'm looking at the
right things then. That's perfect. Yeah.
Yeah.
>> Every like the if you go back like three
and a half years ago when we started
using the term agentic engineering
everyone's like no that's stupid. It it
doesn't mean anything. It it sounds like
a scientific or or medical procedure. Um
and and you know that that only inspires
us to try more and do more. So you know
we're on the right track.
>> Amazing. Ruth, it's been an absolute
pleasure. Thank you very very much for
all the insights and I and I hope our
listeners enjoyed it as much as I did
chatting with you. So uh thanks again.
>> Yeah, my pleasure and thanks for having
me today.
>> Absolutely. And uh for those for those
listening, please join us uh well first
of all subscribe, like the video and
please join us for the next for the next
tune in to the next episode as well.
Thank you very much.
[Music]